<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The man of sin discover'd or George Whitehead unmask't. And his sheep's clothing pull'd off, that his wolvish nature and spirit may be seen. By several instances of G.VV's lyes, false accusations, and base perversions in his book, entituled Judgement fixed, &amp;c. wherein, altho he subscribes himself a constant servant of Christ, yet by his fruits he's discover'd to obey Antichrist.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08855</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6952A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064145</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2907:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The man of sin discover'd or George Whitehead unmask't. And his sheep's clothing pull'd off, that his wolvish nature and spirit may be seen. By several instances of G.VV's lyes, false accusations, and base perversions in his book, entituled Judgement fixed, &amp;c. wherein, altho he subscribes himself a constant servant of Christ, yet by his fruits he's discover'd to obey Antichrist.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>P. 16 signed: T. Crisp.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Swarthmore College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Judgment fixed.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Man of Sin Diſcouer'd</hi> OR George Whitehead UNMASK'T.</head>
            <head type="sub">And his Sheep's Clothing pull'd off, that his Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Nature and Spirit may be ſeen.</head>
            <head type="sub">By ſeveral Inſtances of <hi>G. VV</hi>'s Lyes, Falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and baſe Perverſions in his Book, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Judgment Fixed,</hi> &amp;c. wherein, altho he Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes himſelf a conſtant Servant of Chriſt, yet by his Fruits he's diſcover'd to obey Antichriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>His Servants you are whom you obey.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="preface">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>For Preface, I deſire thee, without Partiality, and in Patience to read and conſider theſe Seriptures following, which are not here produc't as a Warrant for my Proceedings in this Diſcovery, but as a Caution to ſome, that they be not haſty in Judging it.</p>
               <q>In thoſe days I ſaw Jews that Marryed Wives of Aſhdod, &amp;c. And their Children ſpake half in the Speech of Aſhdod — then I reproved and curſed them, and ſmote certain of them, and pulled off their Hair. — And one of the Sons of Jojada, the Son of Eliaſhip, the High Prieſt, was the Son in Law of Samballat the Horonite, but I chaſed him from me. <bibl>Neh. chap. 13. verſ. 23, 24, 25, 28.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>He that troubleth you, ſhall bear his own Burden, whoever he be, <bibl>Gal. 7.11.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>GEORGE WHITEHEAD,</hi> the Spirit which guides thee in this wicked work is already manifeſt not to be the Long-Suffering Spirit of Chriſt, but the Spirit of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> as in all <hi>Six Babels,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Innoc. Vindic.</hi> may be ſeen; which the Reader is referred to, not for want of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192239:2"/> better Proof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſays, but to prevent <hi>Repitition,</hi> and he doth the ſame, he refe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore in thus doing, that he condemns others for, he is inexcuſable. I ſhall not trace him in all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine perverſe <hi>Windings,</hi> but inſtance ſome of his wicked <hi>Doings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides many other ill Names, as <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Devil Incarnate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> he often terms <hi>W. R. F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C. <hi>Informers,</hi>
                  </hi> and flouriſhes it out with all the aggravations he can, as <hi>Apoſtate, perſecuting, malicious, outragious Informer;</hi> conſidering the time he takes to render us ſuch <hi>abhorrid Informers,</hi> when ſcarce any Perſon in the Nation ſo obnoxious as <hi>Informers,</hi> it may be thought he intended us no good; but he hath in this diſcovered himſelf to be of the Generarion of Perſecutors by their own Principle; for they ſay of one, <hi>He's guilty of perſecuting with the Tongue, which is one in nature,</hi> &amp;c. This is thy own <hi>Judgment Fixt</hi> on thy ſelf; and <hi>G. W.</hi> has hereby made ſo great a Rent in the <hi>Sheep's Cloathing,</hi> he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> appears in, that their <hi>Wolviſh Spirit</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> is ſeen; and thou <hi>G. W.</hi> haſt hereby ſpared me ſome Labour in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmasking</hi> you; for this is proof of your <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> therefore for ſhame call no more for Proofs thereof, nor think to excuſe your ſelves by accuſing others, for that will not clear you, but prove you, <hi>Accuſers of the Brethren.</hi> Several other Inſtances I could give of your Doings, which by your own Rule prove you Perſecutors; as, your <hi>rendring</hi> thoſe Friends who cannot conform to your <hi>Forms</hi> (who be many in ſeveral Counties) <hi>Perverſe</hi> and <hi>Vnpeaceable <hi>in their Converſations:</hi>
                  </hi> now <hi>G. W. <hi>Perſecution</hi>
                  </hi> is <hi>Sin, and he that commits Sin, is of the Devil.</hi> Therefore thou art not a <hi>Conſtant Servant of Chriſt</hi> (as thou falſly ſubſcribes thy ſelf) <hi>but a perſecuting</hi> One, of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and therefore not to be heard, but to be turned from and chaſed away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>G. W.</hi> in the Contents of his third <hi>Section,</hi> ſays of <hi>W. R. He is prov'd guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reproaching the</hi> Quakers <hi>in general.</hi> I have examined that third <hi>Section,</hi> and find no ſuch Proofs; but thou cites from <hi>Ch. Qu.</hi> Preface, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>W. R.</hi> ſaying, <hi>Theſe kind of Declarations frequently publiſh't among the aforeſaid Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Now of thoſe words of <hi>W. R's,</hi> the <hi>aforeſaid people:</hi> (ſays <hi>G. W.) What mean they but the Quakers in general?</hi> But its evident that by thoſe words <hi>W. R.</hi> meant not the <hi>Quakers in general,</hi> but <hi>ſome</hi> that he had afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named in <hi>pag.</hi> 5. Such as thy ſelf <hi>Geo. <hi>Apoſtate Innovators;</hi>
                  </hi> and thy query<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>what means,</hi> &amp;c. is but <hi>baſely begging the Queſtion,</hi> and that's no Proof: therefore the notorious Untruth thou wouldſt turn on <hi>W. R.</hi> is thy own; but in caſe he had meant, that ſuch unprofitable Doctrines were preach't a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Quakers in general</hi> in their publick Meetings, what <hi>Reproach</hi> is it to them? if ſuch as thee preach among them that which edifies not, how can the <hi>Hearers</hi> help it? Its no Reflexion on them, to diſcover your <hi>wickedneſs;</hi> and thy not proving in that <hi>Section</hi> what thou affirmeſt in the Contents, proves thee a <hi>Falſe Accuſer.</hi> But if to detect the Errours of ſome among any People, be a Reproach to the people in general, then are you the moſt guilty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> of any I know.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Contents</hi> of the ſixth <hi>Section, G. W.</hi> ſays of <hi>W. R. His writing to clear
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192239:2"/> himſelf from giving Judgment on Report, proved untrue by divers Inſtances.</hi> But in that ſixth <hi>Sect.</hi> I find no ſuch Proof, but <hi>G. W</hi>'s confident <hi>ſay-ſo,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times <hi>baſely begging the queſtion;</hi> which is <hi>no proof:</hi> Be aſhamed! of ſuch wicked works, as to put ſuch <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruths</hi> in thy <hi>Front,</hi> and being ſo bold as to ſay, <hi>proved by divers Inſtances,</hi> when as I find none, but ſeveral <hi>queries,</hi> with thy own bare <hi>Affirmative</hi> and <hi>Negative;</hi> which are ſeveral Inſtances of thy being of a <hi>Reprobate Mind,</hi> rather than a <hi>Conſtant</hi> Servant of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Upon <hi>W. R's</hi> Query to <hi>G. Fox</hi> about his having been (as ſome thought) looked on as <hi>that <hi>Prophet,</hi> God ſaid, by Moſes, he would raiſe up,</hi> &amp;c To this ſays <hi>G. W. he doth deny it, in reference to himſelf as a particular Man — only the Truth of the Immortal Seed, Chriſt in him, as in every true Believer.</hi> What <hi>Jeſuits</hi> reſerve, <hi>G.W.</hi> hath in the words; <hi>[particular Man]</hi> is hard to know, but by what is printed, and what I have in <hi>Manuſcript</hi> by me, <hi>G. F.</hi> hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf more than a <hi>Chriſtian Man,</hi> for he blaſphemouſly ſtiles himſelf, to <hi>O. C. THE Son of God,</hi> not a Son, that's too common for him, other <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> be ſuch, therefore he ſaith, <hi>THE Son of God: THE,</hi> by way of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency. <hi>George,</hi> thou couldſt plainly ſhew thy Diſlike for one ſaying, the Scripture was the Rule, ſays thou, <hi>He Idolatrouſly ſets the Scriptures in the place of</hi> Chriſt; but for that wicked <hi>Barbadoes</hi> Judgment, and <hi>G. F's Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſetting himſelf in the place of Chriſt,</hi> I do not find that thou haſt <hi>plainly ſhow'd thy diſlike,</hi> but rather <hi>plainly ſhew'd</hi> thy ſelf to juſtifie the Wicked; but I believe, that unleſs ye repent, altho both you two <hi>Georges</hi> joyn hand in hand, yet you ſhall not go unpuniſh'd. I have an account of ſome Paſſages that paſt betwixt <hi>O. C.</hi> and <hi>G. F.</hi> (in <hi>Manuſcript</hi> ſign'd <hi>J. Stubs</hi>) where <hi>G. F.</hi> ſays, <hi>From him whom the World calls</hi> G. Fox; <hi>who is THE Son of God.</hi> Now it's the <hi>particular Man,</hi> the World calls <hi>G. Fox, and not the Imortal Seed:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Cloak cannot cover his blaſphemous <hi>Deifying</hi> himſelf: and 'tis evident, he did think himſelf, and was thought of by others, above what he ought to be; for the <hi>Immortal Seed</hi> Chriſt, is in every true <hi>Believer</hi> as well as in him; and although others of you do account your ſelves as <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Overſeers,</hi> and have ſaid that God has crown'd you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet I do not find any ſuch <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions</hi> to, and of any of you, as he hath given him, as in 5th. <hi>Babels, pag.</hi> 7. the blaſphemous Expreſſions in a Letter to him. All theſe conſidered, <hi>plainly ſhews</hi> its little worth, what <hi>G. F.</hi> or <hi>G. W.</hi> affirms or denys.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 39. <hi>G. W.</hi> repreſents <hi>W. R.</hi> ſaying, <hi>The</hi> Penman, and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>accounts themſelves Chriſt's Repreſentatives:</hi> and then <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>That's an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth.</hi> So it is of <hi>G. W's,</hi> but not of <hi>W. R's,</hi> for he ſays not ſo, but <hi>W. R.</hi> ſays <hi>I have cauſe to ſuppoſe, that the</hi> Penman, <hi>&amp;c. count themſelves Chriſt's Repreſentatives.</hi> This is no poſitive affirmation, but an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe in <hi>G. W.</hi> to turn <hi>W. R</hi>'s Suppoſition into an Affirmation; therefore the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth</hi> is <hi>G. W</hi>'s beſides the falſe Accuſation.</p>
               <p>Says <hi>G.W.</hi> in pag. 51. to <hi>W. R. Thou haſt told a groſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth, for the</hi> Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>never ſaid, I deſire my Name ſhould be hid,</hi> &amp;c. Now by his ſaying, <hi>he never ſo ſaid;</hi> that implys, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harg'd <hi>W. R.</hi> as ſaying, he had ſo ſaid, which is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192239:3"/> falſe; for <hi>W. R</hi>'s words be, <hi>It appears to me the</hi> Penman <hi>was aſhamed his Name ſhould be publiſhed,</hi> &amp;c. Now herein <hi>G. W.</hi> is chargeable with two groſs <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths.</hi> 1ſt. In charging <hi>W. R.</hi> with one, when there is none there proved. 2dly. In charging him falſely, as ſaying that which he did not ſay: but yet that may appear which is not ſo ſaid; for thou haſt not ſaid thou art a <hi>Lyar and Perſecutor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>G. W.</hi> yet thou appear'ſt ſuch; therefore the groſs <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth</hi> is thine, <hi>George,</hi> and not <hi>W. R's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 91. <hi>G. W.</hi> charges <hi>W. R. That he renders</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c. as ſhewing no Diſlike to the Barbadoes</hi> Paper; and then ſays, <hi>G.W. Oh ſhameleſs Perverter!</hi> So thou art, <hi>G. W.</hi> elſe thou durſt not ſay ſo; when as <hi>W. R.</hi> doth ſay, and thou confeſſeſth the ſame, that G. F. <hi>doth diſlike ſome part thereof:</hi> and thou (to make <hi>W. R.</hi> ſeem to contradict himſelf) doſt cite three Sentences of his, wherein he grants ſome Diſlike is ſhown: and herein <hi>G. W.</hi> doth pervert <hi>W. R's</hi> words; which be after he had cited ſome Paſſages of <hi>G. F</hi>'s daubing with the Subſcribers; then of thoſe words, ſays <hi>W. R. THIS ſhews no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike,</hi> &amp;c. Its of thoſe Hypocritical Expreſſions that he ſo ſays, which he had before mentioned, and not of <hi>G. F</hi>'s whole Letter, although <hi>G. W.</hi> to colour his Perverſion, doth change <hi>W. R's</hi> firſt word <hi>THIS</hi> for <hi>AS,</hi> becauſe the word <hi>THIS</hi> was not for his Purpoſe. But <hi>G. W's</hi> Forgery and Perverſion ſhows that their <hi>Church Authority</hi> is not defended by <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Honeſty;</hi> but <hi>Forgery</hi> and <hi>Lyes,</hi> &amp;c. be the chief Towers of their <hi>Babel.</hi> O that you of the <hi>Second-days Meeting,</hi> who pretend you are <hi>Overſeers</hi> of Chriſt's Church, ſhould be ſo blind or partial as to ſuffer ſuch things to be Printed and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Spirit of Chriſt. But however that Point is gained of you, that a high grown Church of <hi>G. F</hi>'s have erred, and therefore your Pretenſions to the Orderings and Power of God's Spirit for your <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> will little avail without ſome better Evidence than your own <hi>Say-ſo;</hi> and Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us 'tis true, that a particular may not be in Unity with your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and yet not be erred from their own Meaſures, as <hi>G. F.</hi> falſly ſays. And <hi>G. W.</hi> thy covering of your <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> and daubing with the Subſcribers, under the pretence of <hi>Charity,</hi> manifeſts for what and to whom your <hi>Charity</hi> is, even to ſuch as can <hi>give up all,</hi> &amp;c. a pair of charitable <hi>Georges</hi> indeed; as can paſs by ſuch ſmall Faults, as giving up all <hi>Spirituals</hi> and <hi>Temporals</hi> to your Spirit: but if another (or rather the Printer) miſ-ſpel a word, that you can publiſh in Print for four Errours, as in <hi>J.F</hi>'s Book entituled, <hi>A Few Words,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some Obſervations on <hi>G. W</hi>'s Letter to <hi>F. B.</hi> in Iudgment Fixed.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding <hi>G. W's</hi> Pretenſions of <hi>Concern of Conſcience</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Letter, yet Money ſeems to be his great Concern, as is evident by his being in ſo great a rage, as appears by his vomiting out ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and defaming terms to <hi>F.B.</hi> Viz. <hi>Defrauder, Over-reacher, unreaſonable Impoſer, Arbitrary, conceited Fool,</hi> &amp;c. And I find te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pages moſtly ſpent about
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192239:3"/> 15 <hi>l.</hi> pay'd to <hi>F.B.</hi> for ſo much he was Fined for S. <hi>Cater's</hi> Preaching, &amp; not tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Name; which Money <hi>F. B.</hi> proffered to return to <hi>S. C.</hi> again, upon his Subſcribing to a Paper, as in <hi>Painted Harlot, <hi>pag.</hi>
                  </hi> 36. may be ſeen at large. The Subſtance was, that <hi>S. C.</hi> ſhould give it as his <hi>Judgment</hi> (not Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) <hi>that all Friends of the Miniſtry ought to tell their Names to Informers, when they come to Convict the Meetings where they be, or Re-imburſe thoſe that ſuffer for their not ſo doing, or be reputed blame worthy.</hi> This <hi>G. W.</hi> renders an <hi>unconſcionable Cannon, illegal Impoſition,</hi> (and terms <hi>F. B. Fool</hi>) but I do not find he hath prov'd it ſo, but himſelf a falſe <hi>Accuſer,</hi> although he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 212. <hi>It exceeds the Conventicle-Act.</hi> But <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays falſe, or elſe that <hi>Act</hi> is very favourable; for were the Extremity of that <hi>Act</hi> of no worſe Conſequence, than to be by <hi>S. C. reputed blameworthy; and noted as ſuch,</hi> ſurely there would not be ſo many diſtreſſed and impriſoned: but for Proof that <hi>F. B's</hi> Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſeverer than the <hi>Conventicle Act, G. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>that Act no where compels Friends to tell their Names to Informers:</hi> Nor doth <hi>F. B's</hi> Propoſition; for they may reimburſe who ſuffer for them, or be reputed blame worthy, <hi>and noted as ſuch</hi> (BUT) by S. C<hi>'s Judgment.</hi> Is not <hi>S. C.</hi> ſome more than ordinary Prelate in <hi>G. F</hi>'s new Church Government? he being ſuch a Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man formerly, when he was for another Intereſt (and lead — <hi>Horſe</hi>) which it may be he then thought, would have prevailed, and been as <hi>G. F.</hi> now is, the Ruling Party, but that failing, he ſoon found another, likely to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his Ends, and ſo, it may be, if <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party ſhould not hold to be the ruling Intereſt, he may turn about to another, as <hi>Ben. Furly</hi> hath, and ſay, he <hi>knew not what Spirit did then influence him:</hi> for ſuch empty Clouds are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly driven with any Winds; but although <hi>G.W.</hi> calls <hi>F.B's</hi> Propoſition, <hi>Cannon, Edict,</hi> &amp;c. yet I know not how he can prove it ſuch, if ſigned by <hi>S. C.</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be ſo, that any one of <hi>G. F's</hi> Preacher's <hi>Judgment</hi> be a <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Edict,</hi> or elſe <hi>S. C.</hi> is ſome extraordinary Prelate of <hi>G. F's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding <hi>G. W</hi>'s Outcry againſt the Propoſition, I ſhall offer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the Reaſonableneſs thereof. 1ſt. It ſeems <hi>Chriſtian-like,</hi> for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to be willing to bear his own Burthen, for fear he make his Preaching chargeable to others, for ſurely if the true Apoſtle would work with his hands, to adminiſter to his Neceſſities, rather than be chargeable to others, then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will, (if able, for its not to be thought he meant others) reimburſe them that ſuffer for him; although the falſe Apoſtles <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp; <hi>S. C.</hi> will not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If its our Duty to bear one anothers Burthens, then much more our own.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But turn <hi>G. W</hi>'s own Argument, <hi>pag.</hi> 215. <hi>That which will not pay</hi> 10 <hi>l. for his Brother</hi> (ſays he) <hi>will not lay down his Life for the Brethren.</hi> But he's more unlikely to lay down his Life for his Brother, who would not lay down his Money to his Brother that ſuffered for him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It manifeſts Diſtruſt in the Preacher, that he preaches not for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Sake, becauſe its promis'd, <hi>That whatever any one ſuffers for Chriſt's Sake, it ſhall be reſtored:</hi> and your being ſo unwilling to bear your own Burdens, ſhow that you <hi>have little (if any) of the Apoſtle's Faith, though you</hi> (but falſly) <hi>aſſume ſo much of their POWER.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192239:4"/>5. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ncealing your Names, and ſo ſecuring your Money, you are not good but ill Examples to the Flock, contrary to the true Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By that golden Rule, <hi>Do as you would be done by;</hi> Its equal, that if the Preacher will not ſuffer for another, then he ſhould not let another ſuffer for him; that <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>S. C.</hi> would not ſuffer for <hi>F. B.</hi> is evident by their Judgment and Practice; therefore <hi>S. C.</hi> ſhould not let <hi>F. B.</hi> ſuffer for him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Your not telling your Names, nor reimburſing thoſe that ſuffer for you, ſavours too much of <hi>Self-ſaving,</hi> which is repugnant to Chriſt's Command and Example of <hi>Self-denyal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The <hi>Miniſters</hi> not reimburſing thoſe who ſuffer for them, is ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Chriſtian Nobility</hi> of thoſe (whom that proud <hi>Phariſee G. W.</hi> terms) <hi>a dark ſort of Chriſtians,</hi> as is evident by the Example of <hi>J. Jolly,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Painted Harlot,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 16. That 'tis a ſhame for you <hi>S. C.</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> to come ſhort of them, ſeing you pretend to ſo much more Light than they.</p>
               <p>Therefore for theſe, and more Reaſons that may be given, it ſeems not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable</hi> nor <hi>unconſcionable,</hi> (as <hi>G. W.</hi> falſely implyes) but it is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience that the Preacher ſhould reimburſe who ſuffer for him (if able) or <hi>be reputed Blameworthy,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>G. W.</hi> continues his Rage; (what a Paſſion! a little Money puts this miſerable Wretch <hi>G. W.</hi> in;) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>F. B.</hi> whom he falſly charges in <hi>p.</hi> 212. Says <hi>G. W.</hi> to <hi>F. B. Thou wouldſt enforce on Friends of the Miniſtry, who ſometimes may be ſilent in Meetings,</hi> to tell their Names — But that this is an Untruth, is evident by the words of <hi>F. B</hi>'s Propoſition; for they may chooſe whether they will tell their Names or no, if they will reimburſe thoſe that ſuffer for them; and if none be Fin'd for them, then they have nothing to pay. Therefore <hi>G. W</hi>'s Affirmation that <hi>F. B.</hi> would inforce them to tell their Names, is falſe, and <hi>G. W. forces</hi> an Untruth on the Reader, as well as a falſe Charge againſt <hi>F. B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 212. <hi>G.W.</hi> ſays, that <hi>F. B. would inforce Miniſters, whil'ſt miniſtring,</hi> (or Declaring) to <hi>ſtop and tell their Names,</hi> &amp;c. But they may <hi>reimburſe</hi> thoſe that ſuffer for them, and then need not ſtop to tell their Names: but <hi>G. W.</hi> had need ſtop, and not run on in this his pernitious Current of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths</hi> and <hi>Pervertions,</hi> thus to wreſt things to his own Deſtruction, if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not. But beſides all this which hath been ſaid, the very Beginning and Concluſion of <hi>F. B</hi>'s Propoſition clears it from all theſe <hi>Calumnies G. W.</hi> loads it and <hi>F. B.</hi> with; for its only thus, Viz. <hi>I, S. C. do hereby teſtifie it is my Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. — And in the Concluſion it runs thus, that <hi>ſuch as tell not their Names, nor reimburſe who ſuffer for them, ſhall be</hi> (by <hi>S. C</hi>'s Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>reputed Blame-worthy.</hi> Behold this is the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moſt Severity of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>F. B's</hi> which <hi>G. W.</hi> complains of as ſuch an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſcionable, Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable Cannon;</hi> but I think, to the <hi>Impartial Reader, G. W.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf appears far more <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable, Perverſe,</hi> and <hi>Partial</hi> in ſo terming <hi>F. B's Propoſition:</hi> for <hi>F. B.</hi> did not deſire <hi>S. C.</hi> to ſtamp it with the Titles of <hi>The Judgment or Teſtimony in the word of God's Wiſdom:</hi> or that, <hi>The Riſe, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and Eſtabliſhing thereof was according to the Counſel of God.</hi> I ſay, had <hi>F. B.</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192239:4"/> deſired <hi>S. C.</hi> to ſtamp it with ſuch unfitting Titles as you have your <hi>IDOL G. F</hi>'s Image, <hi>Women's Meetings;</hi> or as you have your wicked <hi>Bull</hi> againſt <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> Then <hi>G. W.</hi> might juſtly object againſt it: but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>F. B.</hi> only deſired <hi>S. C.</hi> to give it as <hi>his Iudgment.</hi> Now with what Face can <hi>G. W.</hi> render <hi>F. B</hi>'s Propoſition as ſuch an <hi>unconſcionable Cannon, Edict,</hi> &amp;c. and yet ſay, that their Laws, by them ſo <hi>Deify'd,</hi> and impos'd as indiſpenſible New Covenant <hi>Ordinances:</hi> (of theſe <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays) <hi>They are tender and Chriſtian Counſel and Advice:</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, that <hi>F. B. abuſes them for their tender Counſel and Advice:</hi> wheras 'tis evident, <hi>F. B.</hi> &amp;c. only op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their indiſpenſible impoſing their new invented <hi>needleſs Imaginations</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on People againſt their Conſciences. And notwithſtanding <hi>F. B.</hi> hath <hi>ſhewn</hi> and <hi>complained</hi> againſt that new and illegal <hi>Practice</hi> of theirs, in making that unlimited Law, <hi>not to <hi>Suffer,</hi> nor <hi>Permit</hi> Marriages without the conſent of two Men's and Women's</hi> (that is, four) <hi>Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. Yet <hi>G. W.</hi> hath the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to affirm, that <hi>F. B. hath not ſhewn nor given them any inſtance of thoſe new Practices among them.</hi> Alſo <hi>G. W.</hi> terms that unlawful and unlimited <hi>Cannon</hi> of theirs, <hi>not to <hi>Suffer</hi> nor <hi>Permit</hi> Marriages without Licenſe from</hi> G. F's <hi>Female Prelates,</hi> &amp;c. as at large may be ſeen in <hi>De Chriſtianâ Libertate pag.</hi> 139. This <hi>G. W.</hi> terms an <hi>Agreement;</hi> which in common acceptation, implyes the conſent of all Parties concern'd, which they cannot pretend to have had in the making that formentioned <hi>Cannon;</hi> and unleſs <hi>G. W.</hi> can prove that <hi>J. A. agreed</hi> to that <hi>Cannon,</hi> it is an Impoſition on him and all concern'd. This partiality in <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> prove them to be thoſe who uſe <hi>falſe Ballances and Meaſures,</hi> (I mean not for his Trade) which is an abomination to the Juſt. I ſay, let the <hi>Impartial</hi> Reader but weigh theſe things in the equal and true Ballance, and then judge whether or no <hi>G. W.</hi> is not very unconſcionable and unchriſtian, to thus groſly pervert, abuſe, and falſly charge <hi>F. B.</hi> and yet have the confidence to ſubſcribe himſelf a <hi>Conſtant <hi>Servant of Chriſt,</hi>
                  </hi> when as theſe wicked works manifeſts him more likely a <hi>Conſtant <hi>Servant of Antichriſt.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS ON <hi>G.W</hi>'s ABUSE OF <hi>T. CRISP</hi> IN HIS BOOK, <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT FIXED. &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>Pag.</hi> 277. <hi>G. W.</hi> charges me with a <hi>Downright <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth,</hi> becauſe in <hi>Teſtimo.</hi> p. 24. I ſay of thoſe aforecited <hi>Teſtimonies, The ſubſtance of the whole is included:</hi> but ſays <hi>G. W. the ſubstance of that Paper of</hi> J. W's <hi>is not included:</hi> but to clear my ſelf from his <hi>downright <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth,</hi> I anſwer, that in <hi>pag.</hi> 23. in the Title, on top of that <hi>Testimony</hi> of <hi>J. W<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>,</hi> I do not term it their ſenſe about <hi>Tithes,</hi> but <hi>their ſenſe about</hi> Women's Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> cannot prove that in that Paper they gave any other or contrary ſenſe about <hi>Women</hi>'s <hi>Meetings</hi> than what I there inſert; but that <hi>G. W.</hi> charges me with, is, for leaving out ſome words about <hi>Tithes;</hi> but unleſs he could prove that I had in that Paper given any thing, as their ſenſe, concerning <hi>Tithes,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192239:5"/> contrary to that he mention'd, its wrong in him to charge me with a <hi>downright <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth:</hi> but <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays to me, <hi>why didſt leave out thoſe words, was there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their ſenſe? &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, yea, there was <hi>of their ſenſe about Tithes,</hi> but not about <hi>VVomen's Meetings,</hi> therefore not needful for me to inſert there, becauſe 'tis entituled, <hi>Their Senſe about <hi>Women's Meetings,</hi>
                  </hi> and not about <hi>Tithes:</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> hath not proved me in a <hi>downright <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth,</hi> but himſelf a <hi>downright <hi>falſe Accuſer.</hi>
                  </hi> Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 299. <hi>G. W.</hi> cites me in 4th. <hi>Babels, pag.</hi> 2. and 3. ſaying, <hi>There is no denyal or diſowning the Principle of giving up all <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> to</hi> G. F<hi>'s Men's and Womens Meetings;</hi> then ſays <hi>G. W.</hi> to me, <hi>this is a groſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth:</hi> but he has not prov'd it ſo, but prov'd himſelf a <hi>groſs Perverter:</hi> for thoſe words of mine which he cites were in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſome Charges of <hi>S. C's</hi> againſt me, and related to ſome particular paſſages out of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Letter, which <hi>S. C.</hi> had brought againſt me, and 'twas of thoſe particular Citations of <hi>S. C</hi>'s out of <hi>G. F's</hi> Letter, which I there ſaid, <hi>Here is no denyal or reproof for giving up all, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo in <hi>pag.</hi> 3. I ſay, <hi>In all</hi> S. C<hi>'s Citations, he hath not proved any Denyal of the Principle, of <hi>Giving up all,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>G. W</hi>'s applying thoſe words of mine to <hi>G. F's</hi> Letter in general, when as they only relate it to thoſe particular paſſages, is a Perverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and inſtead of giving manifeſt Proofs of their diſowning that wicked Principle he gives his own confident <hi>Say-ſo; that their Conſciences bear them witneſs they do deny it:</hi> which proves his own <hi>groſs <hi>Boldneſs</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Partiality;</hi> for they ſay that others <hi>Say-ſo is no Proof:</hi> and if <hi>G. W.</hi> were not more than ordinary confident, he durſt not ſo affirm, <hi>Viz.</hi> That they did plainly ſhew their diſlike to that Paper: but 'tis obſervable, how this Perverter <hi>G. W.</hi> hath varyed the term, for my words are, <hi>The Principle of <hi>Giving up all,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> Now theſe words he changes into the word <hi>Paper,</hi> which makes great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the ſignification: and I never did deny, but always allowed they did diſlike ſome part of that paper, but a <hi>Part</hi> is not the <hi>Whole,</hi> therefore their diſlike is not properly applicable to the Paper in general; ſee it more at large in 1ſt. 4th. and 5th. <hi>Babels, &amp;c.</hi> And becauſe <hi>G. W.</hi> doth ſo confidently affirm <hi>they did plainly ſhew their diſlike,</hi> let the Reader conſider their dealing with <hi>J. P.</hi> for cauſing ſome of their Books to be thrown down publickly on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> near where he burnt a little piece of waſte Paper; becauſe they thought that contempt was thereby ſhown to their books: now this <hi>they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike,</hi> and <hi>plainly <hi>ſhew it,</hi>
                  </hi> for they publiſht in Print, that he was <hi>inſtigated by <hi>the Devil:</hi>
                  </hi> (this <hi>plainly</hi> ſhews diſlike) but no ſuch diſlike to the <hi>Judgment of <hi>Giving up all,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> but on the contrary, highly magnifyed them; although that <hi>Judgment</hi> or <hi>Principle</hi> be of ſo wicked a tendency; but to cover their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Malice,</hi> they f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſly pretend he would have burnt the <hi>Bible;</hi> but their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Writings manifeſt their reſpect to that good Book was not ſo great, but their rage was great; becauſe they thought Contempt was ſhown to their Books. I ſay, theſe conſidered, and their cruel envy in ſhewing their <hi>plain diſlike</hi> to <hi>F. B's Propoſition,</hi> and their Hypocritical flattering them at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> do more <hi>plainly ſhew</hi> their Partiality and Reſpecting of Perſons, than their <hi>plain denyal</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192239:5"/> of that Paper, and <hi>G. W.</hi> obſerve what St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>If we ſay we have Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him, and walk in Darkneſs, we lye.</hi> What then is thy confident ſaying ſo worth, when you act ſo contray? And notwithſtanding <hi>G. W.</hi> hath the confidence to ſay, <hi>Their Conſcience beareth them witneſs, and they have plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed their Diſlike:</hi> yet <hi>S. C.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 1. calls it, <hi>Our Judgment, or the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we take part with.</hi> For ſhame, <hi>G. W.</hi> be not thus <hi>plainly</hi> confuſed and falſe; for herein thou art guilty of <hi>falſe Accuſing, Pervertion,</hi> and a <hi>GROSS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth,</hi> beſides the <hi>Partiality</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> which is herein <hi>plainly ſhewn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Pag. 300. <hi>G. W.</hi> ſeems much offended with me for ſaying in 4th. <hi>Babels,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 8. G. F. <hi>&amp;c. ſharply reprove others, who cannot againſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences give up All, &amp;c.—as the Barbadoes Church hath done, &amp; for not bowing to G. F's Image.</hi> Of this ſays <hi>G. W. What an abominable Lye is this!</hi> and that is his Proof: but to clear me of G. W's <hi>Abominable Lye,</hi> let but their, dealing with <hi>J. P.</hi> aforementioned, and their diſowning <hi>J. A.</hi> alſo their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing me with <hi>Evil,</hi> and <hi>acting contrary to my Conſcience,</hi> and excluding me not only from <hi>Them,</hi> but from the <hi>Faithful;</hi> alſo their wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked <hi>Luciferian Bull</hi> of 66 againſt <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> &amp;c. and what Names they give them, <hi>Viz. Deſpiſers of Heavenly Dignities, bring Confuſion to the Churches, lay waſte the bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Brethren:</hi> and many more black Characters, yet not for Breach of the Command of God, or Law of the Nation, but becauſe they cannot againſt Conſcience conform to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws (which I term, <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Image</hi>) alſo let but their <hi>unconſcionable Preſumptions,</hi> and <hi>unlimited Law,</hi> mentioned in <hi>De Chriſtianâ Libertate,</hi> pag. 60. <hi>Not to Permit nor Suffer Marriages, without the Conſent of two Men's and Women's Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they knew before they made this Law, that there were ſome that would not own their new <hi>Female Government;</hi> alſo, let their ſevere Sentence againſt thoſe that diſcountenance or diſcourage their <hi>New Female Government</hi> by <hi>Women,</hi> ſee <hi>De Christianâ Libertate,</hi> pag. 44. That <hi>if</hi> any Man do but hinder or perſwade his Wife from ſpending what <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Money</hi> ſhe or they will, and if they Judge their <hi>ſo doing,</hi> a <hi>diſcountenancing them in the Work of the Lord,</hi> tho but gathering <hi>Money</hi> for ſuch as <hi>S. Cater,</hi> to give him 10 <hi>l.</hi> at a time; and if after their Admonition any perſiſt in the ſame, they have by that their <hi>Judgment</hi> excluded ſuch out of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church of Chriſt:</hi> Nay, in this their <hi>Luciferian, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Edict</hi> for Confirmation of their New <hi>Female Government,</hi> they ſay of their <hi>Women's Meetings, That the Riſe, Prastice, and ſetting up, and Eſtabliſhment of them — is in the Ordering and Leading of the Eternal Spirit.</hi> Sad were the Condition of many <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others, had theſe Men, <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> any Power in <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st's Church:</hi> but bleſſed be God, we are ſatisfied to the contrary, they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ainly ſhewn</hi> by their Pride and Envy, that they have little to do there, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Power they have in <hi>G. F</hi>'s Church, it's little matter, as long as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot outward Power: alſo they ſay they have Power to determine in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> that is, <hi>Temporal;</hi> and ſay, <hi>That all that are led by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t (G. W</hi>'s, and not Chriſt's) <hi>muſt be of one Mind, cannot be otherwiſe.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192239:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> I think it is evident to the <hi>Impartial Reader,</hi> that they do more than ſharply reprove ſuch as cannot againſt their Conſciences, <hi>Give up all, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal,</hi> &amp;c. for many of theſe concerned in the aforemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioned cannot againſt their Conſciences <hi>Give up to be of their M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd in Spirituals and Temporals;</hi> ſo that if we muſt be all of one Mind whatever they require, <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals and Temporals muſt be given up;</hi> See 1ſt. <hi>Babels.</hi> Therefore I think it <hi>plainly proved</hi> they ſharply reprove and that by this their procedure, they do what in them lye to compel People to <hi>give up all.</hi> All theſe conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that <hi>G. W.</hi> gives no Proofs of his Charge againſt me but his <hi>Say-ſo,</hi> I hope that the Impartial Reader is ſatisfied that my ſaying, <hi>They ſharply reprove thoſe which cannot give up all <hi>Spirituals</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Temporals,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> &amp;c. is not an <hi>Abominable Lye:</hi> but its obſervable how <hi>Jeſuilitically</hi> G. W. inſinuates this high Charge, for although he would have the unwary Reader think it ſo, yet he dare not be ſo abominable bold as to poſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, but baſely begs the Queſtion, ſaying, <hi>What an abominable Lye is this!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, in <hi>p.</hi> 300. <hi>G. W.</hi> ſeems much offended at my ſaying in 4th. <hi>Babels, pag.</hi> 7. That <hi>they endeavour to compel all to worſhip their Image.</hi> And in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. I ſay, <hi>that they will drive thoſe that will not follow them, contrary, or before the Spirit lead them, into their Ceremonies.</hi> Theſe <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>be ſcornful, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, foul, and falſe ſlanders.</hi> But I find no <hi>notorious</hi> Proof thereof, only <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays it: but in 1ſt. 2d. 3d. 4th. and 5th. <hi>Babels</hi> I have ſufficiently proved your <hi>Compelling,</hi> and to them I refer the Reader: alſo theſe aforenamed Inſtances of <hi>your excluding</hi> from the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all who cannot Conform to you,</hi> and your <hi>cruel envious Perſecuting by all the Power you yet have:</hi> theſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your <hi>Compelling Spirit,</hi> as in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14. it's ſaid, <hi>Why compellest thou the Gentiles?</hi> &amp;c. Now he had no power to compel, but by perſwading them, <hi>That unleſs they were Circumciſed, and kept Moſes's Law, they could not be ſaved,</hi> Acts 15. And that, in Scripture ſenſe is <hi>Compelling,</hi> and <hi>You</hi> have done as much, and therefore my Charge is not <hi>notorious falſe,</hi> but thou <hi>G. W.</hi> art <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Confident</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> to deny that which is ſo <hi>plainly</hi> true; and therefore herein the <hi>notorious, foul, falſe Slanderer</hi> is thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>G. W. in his <hi>pag.</hi> 301. charges me with <hi>Confident Credulity</hi> for repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Paper</hi> or <hi>Viſion</hi> in <hi>Testimonys, pag.</hi> 12. as <hi>Ed. Burroughs,</hi> and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents it as <hi>John Perrots;</hi> but herein he is guilty of that he condemns me for, <hi>Viz. Confident Credulity,</hi> for he only produces ſome Perſons from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> that ſay they have ſeen it with <hi>J. P</hi>'s Name to it, but others have ſeen it with <hi>Ed. Burroughs</hi> Name to it, ſo that I ſtand on equal terms with him in that; but alſo one of <hi>G. W</hi>'s Brother Preachers hath granted to me that it was ſome other <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> B.</hi> although not <hi>E. Burrough,</hi> which if ſo, then it cannot be <hi>J. P</hi>'s, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> repreſents it, but he too <hi>confidently Credulous;</hi> neither have I in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dition aſſign'd it to <hi>E. Burrough,</hi> but <hi>E. B.</hi> for it is not the Name of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hor that induced me to puliſh it, but the Service of the Matter, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> been ſpoke by <hi>Balaam's Aſs,</hi> ought not to be diſeſteemed: and if I was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in aſſigning it to <hi>E. Burrough,</hi> then thou <hi>G. W.</hi> art not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192239:6"/> excuſable in repreſenting it <hi>J. P</hi>'s, but as guilty as I am; yet I believe thou wouldſt think thy ſelf hardly dealt by, if I ſhould call thee ſuch Names as ſome of thy Brethren have done me about that, (falſly affirming it to be <hi>J. P</hi>'s) ſaying that I am <hi>Joyn'd with the Devil, paſt ſhame, ſold my ſelf to work wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, impudent Face,</hi> and many more ſuch terms have I had by <hi>Poſt</hi> (to put me to Charge) without any Name, or Place from whence: but this action and the Language ſhows its from G. F. or ſome of his <hi>Adherents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for thoſe words of mine in <hi>Teſt. pag.</hi> 26. <hi>Viz. If any obſerve not to do juſt as others, in Tythes and other Civil Rights,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words <hi>G. W.</hi> is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at, ſaying in his <hi>pag.</hi> 272. That I do <hi>account</hi> Tyths <hi>amongst Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Rights;</hi> but he miſapplies my words; although I confeſs, I might more fully and properly expreſt my ſelf, conſidering what a Perverſe Generation I had to do wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h: but had <hi>G. W.</hi> been in the <hi>Spirit of Charity</hi> (which he falſly pretends to) with the <hi>Salvo</hi> of <hi>not strictly or moſt proper,</hi> and the allowance of <hi>Faleor in Syntax:</hi> as ſuch Excuſes he can find for more unſound and <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Expreſſions of G. F.) he might have allowed, that in ſome ſenſe, my words are not ſo intollerable as he renders them, conſidering, that in ſome Places, <hi>Tythe</hi> ſo called, is particular Perſons, (<hi>Laymen</hi>'s, not <hi>Clergymen</hi>'s) proper Eſtates by Inheritance; and in ſuch Caſes, I know not but <hi>Tyths</hi> ſo called, may be term'd a <hi>Civil Right;</hi> not that I take on me to determine them ſo (as due by Equity originally, but as Outward or Temporal Concerns, as <hi>Cole Tax,</hi> &amp;c. But your great Advantage againſt them, lyes in that term, or word <hi>[TYTHE]</hi> but if the Authority of the Nation ſhould tax the ſame Perſons the ſame value as their <hi>Tythe</hi> under the denomination of <hi>Tribute,</hi> or other Name, as to them ſeem meet, and impower ſome <hi>Civil Officer</hi> to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it, as they do other <hi>Taxes,</hi> altho they imploy them to the ſame Uſes, I ſee not but great part of the Strength of many of your Arguments would be abat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it not being for you, as private <hi>Subjects</hi> to queſtion or aſſign how, or to whom the Authority diſpoſes of any <hi>Taxes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 273. G. W. doth falſly render me as pleading for them to be led by the Spirit, <hi>to pay <hi>Tithes,</hi> who have really been convinced of the Evil thereof.</hi> That <hi>G. W.</hi> doth intend thus to render me, is evident from theſe his words, <hi>Viz. Thou couldſt never ſuppoſe that any meaſure of Grace would allow any, who have been convinced of the evil thereof</hi> [Tythes] <hi>in the Payment of them.</hi> But G. W. hath not, nor can produce me any where ſo ſaying, but its an abſolute <hi>Forgery</hi> of his own, and plainly ſhews him a <hi>Slanderer</hi> and <hi>falſe Accuſer.</hi> But this I do ſay, that ſome may refuſe to do ſome things, thinking that they are by the Spirit <hi>convinced of the Evil thereof,</hi> but be miſtaken, and <hi>be influenced by the wrong Spirit,</hi> that guides thee; but in time may be <hi>reſtored to better Judgment;</hi> and not take your Commands for <hi>New-Covenant Ordinances,</hi> but find that they are but <hi>Men's Traditions,</hi> and that for fear, and to pleaſe you, they did do, and refuſe to do ſome things, and yet not render the Spirit of God to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it ſelf, but contradictory to your Spirit; and thy thus <hi>forging</hi> a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, proves thee, not a <hi>Constant Servant of Chriſt,</hi> but of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:192239:7"/>
               <p>As it is evident by thy perverting <hi>R. R's</hi> words, in <hi>Teſt.</hi> pag. 22. where he ſays, <hi>In all Forms the Lord hath of his People—fitted to act in all Forms, as the Lord their Light ſhall lead them.</hi> This <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays in pag. 281. <hi>Tends to Rantiſme:</hi> but proves it not, but ſays, <hi>His</hi> (i. e. Gods) <hi>Light doth not lead the Children of the Free Woman to act in all Forms,</hi> &amp;c. Neither doth <hi>R. R.</hi> any where ſo ſay, only, that <hi>they are fitted to act in all Forms, as the Lord ſhall lead them.</hi> So that by <hi>R. R</hi>'s words, they are not fitted to act in any <hi>Form</hi> the Lord doth not lead them into, but as he leads them into any Form, they are fitted to act therein; and <hi>G. W.</hi> I think herein thou haſt ſpoke more <hi>Truth</hi> than thou wert aware of, for I believe the Lord hath many Children whom he doth not, nor ever will lead into your Form (of <hi>Female-Prelates</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> although you impoſe them as <hi>indiſpenſible New-Covenant Ordinances</hi>) to act therein, therefore, not <hi>All</hi> Forms, as thou ſaiſt: but that which <hi>R. R.</hi> intended by thoſe words, was to ſhow his <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> to ſome honeſt minded amongſt you and other diſtinct <hi>Forms</hi> of Profeſſours of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that <hi>THEY</hi> were accepted of God, not in reſpect to your Form afore others, but as <hi>they loved and feared the Lord, doing that which is juſt,</hi> ſays <hi>R. R.</hi> And this Spirit of <hi>Charity</hi> to other Perſwaſions, is to you <hi>proud Phariſees,</hi> a Rock of Offence and Stumbling Stone (but <hi>precious</hi> to the <hi>Meek</hi> and <hi>Upright hearted</hi>) and is that you hate, and endeavour to deſtroy; (read your <hi>Figure</hi> in <hi>Eſau</hi>) in whom, or whereever it is brought forth, and after which the Dragon, through you, caſts ſuch Floods of Wickedneſs and falſe Accuſations: and although the Rage of <hi>Eſau</hi> may for a time cauſe <hi>Jacob</hi> to flee, yet he is bleſt, and ſhall be bleſt, and the Mount of Lordly <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall be laid waſte. Read who can.</p>
               <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 285. <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays that <hi>R. R. gives no particular Inſtance of their Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but bids them witneſs the hat:</hi> but he doth mention their aſſuming Power to judge in Caſes of Controverſy, &amp; their Impoſing their Judgment on their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, on pain of being rejected, <hi>as joyned to Heathens,</hi> &amp; other particulars <hi>R. R.</hi> mentions, which are more than <hi>witneſs the Hat;</hi> and do <hi>witneſs</hi> thee <hi>G. W.</hi> a falſe Accuſer, who in <hi>pag.</hi> 280. ſays of <hi>J. P.</hi> that <hi>He is offended at the Form of Sound Words,</hi> THEE <hi>and</hi> THOU: and this becauſe he ſays to G. F. <hi>Away with your Set Form of Words</hi> Thee <hi>and</hi> Thou: but its YOU wicked Ones, to whom he ſhew'd your Abominations in many particulars, as may be ſeen in his Letter in Print to G. F. I ſay, it's you <hi>Wicked Ones</hi> G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to whom he ſays, <hi>Away with your Set Forms,</hi> &amp;c. It's not the words <hi>Thee and Thou,</hi> for he allows them to be proper Speech enough, neither doth he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn any that uſe them out of Conſcience, or in Simplicity; and <hi>G. W.</hi> had the Man of Sin been at that Stature and height of wickedneſs in any, in the days of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as he is come to in thee, when <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>My Soul hateth your New Moons,</hi> &amp;c. He might have accuſed the Prophet, for ſpeaking againſt the Commands of God, by the ſame Rule as thou charges <hi>J. P.</hi> Therefore away with thy perverſe and falſe accuſing Spirit, G. W. <hi>Its not the Spirit of true Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And G. W. thou ſeems very impudent to charge me in Print, to abuſe my Wife; but <hi>George,</hi> it is not I, but thou, that haſt abuſed her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d me in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192239:7"/> us in Print to the World, as at variance, for from thy ſcandalous and ſo often charging me, as abuſing her, it was thought by ſome that knew us not, that we lived in diſcontent; but <hi>G. W.</hi> and his Brother in Iniquity, <hi>J. F.</hi> could not effect that, and I hope, never ſhall; and for all thou term'ſt us <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Devils Incarnate,</hi> and prateſt of the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>W. R.</hi> but thou haſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in manifeſted more familiar Converſe with that <hi>Evil Spirit</hi> than any of thoſe thou ſo terms; as alſo, witneſs thy charging me to act or Sin againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And my Wife doth not think it any Abuſe to let the World know ſhe was deceived in and by you, and that you are not what you pretended to be, and once ſhe and my ſelf thought you were (your Fruits have made you manifeſt; but for the word <hi>[CHEAT]</hi> thou art offended at, it was your own term given me in Print, and returned to you again, as more properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to thoſe among you that Preach, and have wronged ſeveral People. And <hi>George,</hi> thou haſt not, nor canſt thou prove thy <hi>falſe charging</hi> me, <hi>to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe my Wife;</hi> but I ſhall ſay the leſs, becauſe where I am known, I thank God, thy Impudence therein cannot hurt me; but thine, and <hi>J. F</hi>'s Provocation is ſo great, it is hard to be born; for ſuch is the height of thy Envy againſt me, that you are not ſatisfied with doing what you can to raiſe Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween my Wife and me, and render me <hi>abuſing her,</hi> but alſo thou repreſents me as one that will <hi>ſign, own, or ſet my hand to that which is not my own;</hi> and ſo not only a <hi>Cheat,</hi> but what worſe you pleaſe. For ſays <hi>G. W.</hi> to me, <hi>pag.</hi> 291. <hi>IF it be thy own — however it is Patroniſed by thee.</hi> But hereby <hi>G. VV.</hi> thou haſt rendred thy ſelf more like a <hi>CHEAT</hi> than me, to ſubſcribe thy ſelf a <hi>Conſtant Servant of Chriſt,</hi> and yet do ſuch Works of Darkneſs; for hear what one of thy Brethren <hi>R. S.</hi> ſays to <hi>F. B.</hi> about the word <hi>IF:</hi> ſays he, <hi>Thou would fain come out with a Poſitive Aſſertion,</hi> IF <hi>it were not a Downright Lye; of which it may be, then art Conſcious to thy ſelf.</hi> Now <hi>G. W.</hi> ſee if this be not thy own Caſe, and plainly proves thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> guilty of doing that you condemn others for; which G. W. thou haſt ſaid is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian,</hi> beſides the Slander that is inſinuated by thy word <hi>IF.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 293, and 294. G. W. charges me with <hi>acting contrary to my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and to be irreligious, at my will and pleaſure to lay Religion aſide.</hi> And this he proves only by perverting my words, in 4th. <hi>Babels, p.</hi> 19. where I ſay, <hi>I condeſcended to take my Wife in the preſence of a Prieſt, and acquainted him, that I did it not on account of Religion, but to anſwer the Law.</hi> Now thoſe words, Viz. <hi>I did it not on account of Religion,</hi> G. W. perverſly applyes to the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Concern of <hi>Marriage;</hi> as if I ſaid I did not <hi>Marry</hi> on account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but that is only his Pervertion; thoſe words are only relating to the <hi>Form;</hi> I did not think that <hi>Form,</hi> of declaring it in his Preſence any more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious than other ways. And its in the <hi>Form</hi> that I placed the Indifferency, as my next words ſhew, <hi>Viz. But to anſwer the Law.</hi> And I placed not the <hi>Indifferency</hi> in the weighty <hi>Concern of Marriage,</hi> as <hi>G. W.</hi> falſly inſinuates: for formerly, when Friends publiſhed their <hi>Marriages,</hi> ſome to the <hi>Juſtices</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:192239:8"/> or in the <hi>Market Place,</hi> there might be as much Religion in the one as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for G. F. in his <hi>Orders</hi> ſays, <hi>They may declare it to the next Juſtice, or in the Market Place, or they may not,</hi> ſays he; (altho he hath made another Law ſince) for one <hi>Form</hi> is no more Religious than another, and that is the true meaning of my words, and not as G. W. perverts them, to render me as one <hi>that hath layed Religion aſide;</hi> which I believe, he doth not out of any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, but wilfully and on purpoſe to make me Odious to honeſt People.</p>
               <p>In Pag. 296. G. W. draws a wicked Concluſion, ſaying, <hi>Therefore</hi> T. C. <hi>&amp;c. may be good Chriſtians, whil'ſt thus inconſiſtent with their Conſciences.</hi> But I deny his Principles and Practices, and this his perverſe Concluſion is not deducible from my words, but is a Slander of his own inventing, for what I plead for, is, that People may be free to act according to their Conſciences, and not againſt them; therefore unleſs G. W. can prove that I have pleaded for any ſuch <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſcionable Liberty,</hi> he is a <hi>Falſe Perverter,</hi> as further appears in <hi>page</hi> 162. in the Contents of the 6th. <hi>Sect.</hi> ſays G. W. of me, <hi>He proved Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious.</hi> So that his own baſe begging the Queſtion, he terms <hi>Proof;</hi> for in his 6th. <hi>Section,</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 294. as the Maſter of <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Inquiſition Office,</hi> ſays G. W. to me, <hi>How Irreligious waſt thou in it!</hi> As if I had been like his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>John Tyſoe</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor:</hi> and if ſuch Men as G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their Queſtions may be admitted as <hi>Prov'd Charges</hi> of ſo weighty a Concern, as to prove a Man <hi>Irreligious,</hi> who knows what may be the Conſequence thereof! But hereby he hath DISCOVERED himſelf to be an IRRELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS <hi>Slanderer,</hi> and therein, <hi>Antiſcriptural.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> After G. W. hath drawn his <hi>falſe Concluſion</hi> as the Conſequence of my Judgment, he ſays to me, <hi>Thus inconſiſtently thou mightſt as well argue for the</hi> Chriſtian-Quakers <hi>paying Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. And then further ſaith, <hi>But I muſt deny the Conſequence.</hi> I anſwer, So do I, G. W. deny <hi>Thee</hi> and thy <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence too,</hi> and tell thee, that its an Untruth for thee to infer from my <hi>pleading</hi> that one may pay <hi>Tythes,</hi> who is not convinced of any Evil therein (for it cannot with Honeſty be ſuppoſed I intended any other) That the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of this is, that others may pay <hi>Tythes</hi> whil'ſt inconſiſtent with their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: I ſay, it is ſo far from being the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of my Judgment, that it's quite contrary to it: therefore thou G. W. in this art a very <hi>falſe Accuſer</hi> and <hi>Perverter;</hi> for that is the main thing I oppoſe and teſtifie againſt you for. Becauſe that by your ſo ſtrict enjoyning your <hi>Ceremonies</hi> on People, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating thoſe that cannot conform to you, not only from <hi>Your Society,</hi> but out of the <hi>Church of Chriſt:</hi> and by this your Severity you compel ſome to be <hi>Hypocrites;</hi> who to pleaſe you, ſometimes act things <hi>inconſiſtent with their Conſciences:</hi> which is inconſiſtent with your firſt Principles.</p>
               <p>I intended ſome further Diſcovery of this <hi>Man of Sin</hi> in G. W's Book: but finding the ſame Spirit in a Book, Entituled, <hi>Righteous Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>R. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diland;</hi> who being of another Nation, I ſhall not take notice of, but the <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> and <hi>Approvers</hi> of his Work, G. W. and the reſt of <hi>G. F</hi>'s chief Prelates of the <hi>Second days Meeting</hi> concerned, who in that Book of <hi>R. S's</hi> ſpeak ſo much in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192239:8"/> the ſpeech of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> that thoſe who have <hi>Ears to hear</hi> may know they are of the Kindred of <hi>Sanballat</hi> (the Enemy of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) that good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> chaſed away: for Proof whereof, conſider their Wrath and Mockery, in <hi>Page</hi> 97.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Team, Rogers, Criſp, Penniman, Bullock and Bugg,</l>
                  <l>Dark, Divel-driven, Dungy Gods deſperately lugg.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Obſerve Reader, firſt by their Term, <hi>Team,</hi> they render us five as a <hi>Team of Horſes,</hi> beſides the other black Characters, as <hi>Dark, Devil-driven, Dungy-Gods.</hi> Theſe ſeem to be the <hi>Mockers</hi> and <hi>Scoffers</hi> that the Apoſtle ſaid ſhould ariſe; and notwithſtanding G. W. and his Brethren have thus Printed Us, as ſuch to be <hi>Abhorred <hi>Creatures,</hi>
                  </hi> yet they have the Impudence to ſay, <hi>That Chriſt never taught to call Friends ſuch Names as FOXONIANS</hi> (which is only uſed for diſtinction of their Party from the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general) then ſurely it may be concluded, Chriſt was not their Teacher in theſe envious Terms, but that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was <hi>G. Whitehead's</hi> and his Brethren's Teacher herein, or elſe they would not have the Impudence to ſay, <hi>The Almighty God knows we never <hi>Endeavoured</hi> to Compel any to a Conformity — who were not fully ſatisfied in their Minds thereto.</hi> If they will allow that to be <hi>Compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> what is in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſo accounted, then they are already proved guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, in 3d. <hi>Babels,</hi> pag. 2. but if they will admit of nothing to be term'd <hi>Impoſition</hi> or <hi>Compelling</hi> but Outward Force, then I confeſs thy have not as yet Power ſo to do; but if none but ſuch be properly <hi>Compelling,</hi> then <hi>Peter</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers concern'd with him, to whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in the <hi>Galathians, Why compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thou the Gentiles?</hi> — were not guilty; for they had no Power to uſe Outward Force any more than you have; but in Scripture Senſe, the ſtrict enjoyning of Outward things, as an <hi>Abſolute Neceſſity,</hi> and as the indiſpenſible Ordinances of the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> and without an exact Conformity thereto, will not admit them to be of the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> is <hi>COMPELLING;</hi> which you have more than <hi>Endeavoured</hi> to do, for you <hi>HAVE</hi> ſo done to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your Power, to thoſe who are ſo far from being FULLY ſatisfied in their Conſciences, that they are not AT ALL SATISFIED therein, as is already proved, <hi>pag.</hi> 9, 10. by your Excommunicating thoſe from the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> who incourage not their <hi>Women's Meetings,</hi> as alſo their Law, <hi>Not to</hi> SUFFER <hi>Marriages without the Licence of two</hi> Women's Meetings, as in <hi>pag.</hi> 7. more at large may be ſeen. Surely, if they were not given up to that Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit that prevailed on <hi>Ahab's</hi> Prophets, they durſt not have the Face to call the Almighty God to witneſs to ſo <hi>Groſs an Untruth,</hi> Viz. <hi>That they have not <hi>Endeavoured</hi> to Compel any to a Conformity — who were not</hi> FULLY <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in their Minds thereto.</hi> Theſe Untruths are the Speech of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and diſcovers you to be Children of <hi>Strange Wives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now by theſe ſeveral Inſtances of G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their LYES, PERSECUTION, FORGERY, SLANDERS, PERVERSIONS, alſo <hi>G. W</hi>'s ſcornful and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful Terms in many places, <hi>Viz. Reſemble the Devil,</hi> the <hi>Devil &amp;</hi> W. R. <hi>gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy headed Fool,</hi> &amp; his likening W. R. to a <hi>Snarling Dog,</hi> and terming us DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VILS, DEVILS INCARNATE, and many more ſuch black Names, it appears.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:192239:9"/>
               <p>If it be true, as <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>pag.</hi> 212. <hi>Chriſt never taught to call Friends FOX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONIANS;</hi> then ſurely Chriſt was not his Teacher in theſe ſcurrilous Names aforenamed; but theſe do manifeſt <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp;c. to be thoſe <hi>grievous Wolves</hi> which the Apoſtle foretold ſhould enter after his Departure, and alſo which Chriſt bid beware of. For this G. W. hath not only belyed and abuſed us, but he has belyed the Lord, in fathering theſe his wicked Actions on the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Righteous Judgment:</hi> but his unrighteous Fruits do prove him, not a <hi>Conſtant Servant of Chriſt,</hi> as he falſly ſubſcribes himſelf, but a Servant of the Covetous and falſe Accuſing Spirit of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel;</hi> which becauſe <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> could not yield to part with his Inheritance, therefore they falſly accuſe him of <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> which thing is not to be read bare as a Hiſtory, but as in Scripture 'tis ſaid, <hi>Theſe Things are an Allegory.</hi> For in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> 2.20. <hi>The Church of Thyatira</hi> is charg'd to ſuffer the Woman <hi>Jezabel,</hi> (who as ſhe doth now, call'd <hi>her ſelf a Propheteſs,</hi> to teach and deceive the Servants of God.</p>
               <p>The ſame Spirit doth now work in G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt ſome who, like <hi>Naboth,</hi> cannot part with the Inheritance of their Fathers (i. e. <hi>the Liberty of their Conſciences</hi>) notwithſtanding <hi>G. F</hi>'s, &amp;c. Pretenſions of <hi>Comely Order,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Ahabs</hi> was for a Garden of <hi>Herbs,</hi> who promiſed as fair as <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> can do, <hi>That he would give a better Vineyard:</hi> but as <hi>Naboth</hi> could not then, ſo cannot many now part with their Inheritance, that is to ſay, forſake the Teachings of the Spirit of Chriſt in their own Hearts, to obey the Commands of G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who are acted by ſuch a wicked Spirit; for if they ſhould, they might thereby, not only enſlave themſelves, but their Poſterity to the Will and Luſt of G. F. G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any ſuch hereafter, that may be ſuffered to put on the <hi>Sheep's Clothing</hi> of good words ſtole from Scripture, to deceive the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Hearted, as they have done: if they have the ſame preſumptious Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to write on the Head of their own Imaginations the ſame, or ſuch Names of <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> as G. F. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have done to their needleſs Imaginations. I oppoſe not the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> in general, or their Principle, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in the Heart or Conſcience of every one, to be thereby taught and led, for of the Truth and Sufficiency thereof I am well ſatisfyed. But it is this <hi>Jezabel's</hi> Spirit that I oppoſe, which doth guide and act this G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is fully diſcovered by the aforementioned <hi>Lyes, Forgeries</hi> and <hi>Slanders,</hi> which are the <hi>Grapes of Sodom,</hi> brought forth by this G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in whom the wicked One is grown to the height and Strength of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> the <hi>Son of Perdition;</hi> for none elſe dare be ſo wicked as to father ſo great wickedneſs upon the Spirit of <hi>Righteous Judgment:</hi> but now the <hi>Sheep's-Cloathing</hi> is pull'd off, from the <hi>Wooviſh Spirit,</hi> which guides G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It will not be ſafe for Friends to follow the Footſteps of this Flock; for they are not the Paths of the Juſt. And if it be true, <hi>They which do Evil hate the Light,</hi> then this G. W. cannot love it, but is an Adverſary thereto. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho the Wicked ſhall do wickedly, and ſhall not underſtand, yet the Humble God will Teach; for whoſe Information this <hi>Diſcovery</hi> is publiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>T. Criſp.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192239:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
